The Charles Henry Kauffman Collection of Materials Relating to Charles Ives
Yale University Music Library
The Charles Henry Kauffman Collection of Materials Relating to Charles Ives
1920-2000
Misc Ms 427
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Chiefly materials pertaining to Charles Ives, from his friend Charles Henry Kauffman
Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired in 2000 from Ralph Braibanti, the son-in-law of Charles Henry Kauffman.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Pennsylvania, Dr. Charles Henry Kauffman practiced osteopathic surgery in Brookfield, Connecticut. Kauffman was a close friend of Charles Ives. The two first met in the 1920s through Ives's brother, Judge J. Moss Ives, and his brother-in-law, the Rev. Joseph Twichell. Dr. Kauffman treated both Charles Ives and his mother for various illnesses, and remained in contact with Ives throughout their lives.
Scope and Contents
Much of the collection pertains to the composer Charles Ives. It includes letters between Kauffman and Ives (as well as other correspondents), published writings and music by Ives, articles concerning Ives, poetry by Kauffman, and a commemorative coin issued in honor of Ives.
Arrangement
Organized into 5 series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings and Music. III. Clippings. IV. Programs. V. Miscellaneous.
Ives, Charles, 1874-1954; Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976
- Correspondence, 1931-1974; Series I
  - 1931, March 3, Ives, Charles (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Date from postmark.
  - 1932, January 3, Ives, Charles (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1932, October 8, Ives, Charles (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Postcard from Paris. Date from postmark.
  - 1942, Ives, Charles (Box 1, Folder 1)
    With typed transcription. Date supplied by Kauffman?
  - 1938, January 6, Ives, Charles (Box 1, Folder 1)
    To President Franklin Roosevelt. Copy of Ives's memoranda concerning the Ludlow bill. Also includes his suggestion for a 20th amendment to the Constitution.
  - 1967, October 6, Ives, Harmony T. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1969, January 25, Ives, Bigelow ("Speck") (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1974, February 25, Jones, Emily G. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1966, October 1, Kirkpatrick, John (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1969, July 15, Maas, Martha (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1967, December 21, Pickett Real Estate (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Signed "Ray and Deb."
  - 1936, April 21, Unidentified correspondent to Edgar Varese (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Copy of original letter.
- Writings and Music, 1920-2000; Series II
  - Essays Before a Sonata. -- New York: Knickerbocker Press., 1920; Ives, Charles, 1815-1880; 124 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Inscribed "to Dr. Charles Kauffman from Charles E. Ives. Sep. 27, '25."
  - 114 Songs., 1921; Ives, Charles, 1815-1880; 1 score (259, [3]p.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Note on flyleaf from Kauffman to Lex and Claire, Sept. 15, 1967.
  - A Connecticut Yankee in Music., 1939; Fletcher, Lucille, 1912-2000; 32 p.; Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "This article was accepted by New Yorker mag., but Ives refused permission to allow publication. Told to me by Ives' nephew Bigelow Ives. Sept. 30, 1965."
  - Writings concerning politics., Ives, Charles, 1815-1880; 13 p.; Photocopy of typescript. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes a copy of his proposed 20th amendment to the Constitution.
  - Notes concerning Ives's purchase of property in Brookfield., ca. 1965; Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976; 2 p.; Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Charles Ives: The Man., Late 1960s; Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976; 21 p.; Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Version 1.
  - Charles Ives: The Man, Late 1960s; Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976; 13 p.; Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Version 2.
  - Charles Ives: The Man., Late 1960s; Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976; 33 p.; Typescript with handwritten corrections. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Version 3. Includes appendix.
  - Selected Poems of Charles Henry Kauffman. Compiled and introduced by Lucy Kauffman Braibanti and Ralph Braibanti., 2000; Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976; 250 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Clippings, 1930-1981; Series III
  - Concerning music, 1965-1974; A.
    - 1965, 6 items (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1966, no date, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1967, 9 items (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1968, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1969, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1971, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1974, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - No date, 9 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Concerning extra-musical information, 1930-1981; B.
    - 1930, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1965, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1966, 6 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1967, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1968, 7 items (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1970, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1971, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1973, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1981, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - No date, 21 items (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Programs, 1931-1974; Series IV; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous, 1942-1975; Series V
  - Charles Edward Ives. -- New York: James T. White & Company., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Offprint from The National Cyclopedia of American Biography.
  - Medallion honoring Charles Ives., 1967; Danbury (Conn.) Coin Club (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Yale., 1968, April (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Yale alumni magazine, with cover story on Charles Ives.
  - Report., 1975, April; Yale University. School of Music. Oral History, American Music (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Report concerning the Ives oral history project.